A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - 1905-1910, n.d. Correspondence: Andrew Carnegie promises to pay for an organ for the University of Virginia and to match the sum of a half million dollars if that amount is raised by the Alumni Association (February 10, 1905); report to Carnegie about the University of Virginia by [Robert Curtis Ogden?] (February 13, 1905); thanks Alderman for the copy of the Jefferson Bible and says about religion, "When we put Jesus with Confucius & the few other Teachers & eliminate an angry father, miracles & all the rest of it the true religious idea purified & exalted will take root & become a vital power for good." (March 15, 1905); and acceptance of an invitation to attend Founder's Day which he was later unable to attend (February 12, 1910). (Box-folder 2:10)
  - 1905 November 22 Correspondence: Grover Cleveland (1837-1908), writes that he is unable to accept the invitation from the Faculty to attend Founder's Day events; original transferred to the Vault (Box-folder 2:11)
  - 1926-1929 Correspondence: Calvin Coolidge (1872-1933), includes the appointment of Alderman to the Sesquicentennial of American Independence and the Thomas Jefferson Centennial Commission (May 5, 1926); originals transferred to the Vault (Box-folder 2:12)
  - 1924-1929 Correspondence: Cosmos Newspaper Syndicate concerning their request to Alderman to join the Cosmos Editorial Board and write an editorial once a month to be published in the most important newspapers in the United States (Box-folder 2:13)
  - 1912-1914 Correspondence: Locke Craig (1960-1925), Governor of North Carolina, refers to the almost certainty of his election as governor (April 25 and June 11, 1912); and refers to a meeting held in Asheville to form the Appalachian Park Association, acquiring land under the Weeks Law, and cooperating with the National Forest Reserve Commission, at which Craig was made President (November 4, 1913) (Box-folder 2:14)
  - 1912-1932, n.d. Correspondence: Charles Richard Crane (1858-1939), offers to help the Aldermans to get advice about Edwin A. Alderman's sickness or to help any way he can (ca. November 1912 and November 26, [1912]); a visit from Dr. Eliot after presiding over the meeting of the Civil Service Association (ca. 1912-1913); mentions that Mr. Brandeis and he are trying to secure an organ for Norman Hapgood and a visit from Sir Horace Plunkett (ca. 1912-1913); describes his visit with the new President [Wilson] who was dictating his first bulletin concerning office-seekers (March 10, 1913); a letter from Alderman outlining the reasons for the success of Woodrow Wilson and the Democratic party (October 30, 1916); and congratulations on Crane's appointment to China (April 3, 1920) (Box-folder 2:15)
  - 1911, 1919 Correspondence: Lewis Dabney Crenshaw (1884-1947), invites Alderman to an alumni event in New York (June 1, 1911) who is unable to come but sends a letter outlining the current condition of the University, its progress, and future expectations (June 5, 1911); Alderman discusses some sort of testimonial for students who left the University to fight in the Civil War and [didn't complete their studies?] such as a veteran reunion at Finals, the impossibility of ever awarding any honorary degree from the University, and his desire to have "some notable reward for high and pure scholarship given to our students who achieve unusual distinction" (December 18, 1911); and several letters from Alderman to Crenshaw when he was the Director of the University of Virginia European Bureau, printed in the Alumni Bulletin (April 1, 9, 1919) (Box-folder 2:16)
  - 1893, 1895 Correspondence: Senator Shelby Moore Cullom (1829-1914), apologizes for not acknowledging the report Alderman sent to him before the special session of Congress (July 24, 1893); and discusses his re-election bid for the Senate and his concerns about the economic condition of the country (January 28, 1895) (Box-folder 2:17)
  - 1896-1903 Correspondence: Jabez Lamar Monroe Curry (1825-1903) sends a letter to Alderman full of high praise for his article on education in the South published in the [?] Review, concurring in every statement and argument (January 3, 1896); in one of two letters to the Reverend William C. Bitting, Pastor Mt. Morris Baptist Church, New York City, Curry praises his article "Why I am a Baptist" and believes it should be published in every Baptist newspaper, stating "Sometimes I am so disgusted with the bigotry, narrow mindedness, intolerance of some Baptist editors, preachers, & private members that I have inquired what refuge is there, where truer catholicity, [Christian]ty, can be found. Like Noah's dove I have returned to the ark, and now your article, so sound, so thoughtful, so edifying & consolatory, assures me, we are right and must wait and pray & labor & hope" (May 19, 1899). In a second letter, he asks that Bitting send him more of the pamphlets like an earlier one on Bible Study sent to Curry (October 6, 1899). Other items include a telegram and two letters from Alice T. Connally to Bitting about Dr. Curry dying and the plans for his funeral service (February 8, 13, [1903]); and a copy of the address by the Reverend William C. Bitting at Curry's funeral (February 15, 1903) (Box-folder 2:18)
  - 1904-1931 Correspondence: D-F, including: A.C. Davis; John Staige Davis; Henry Pomeroy Davison, Chairman of the American Red Cross War Council, inviting Alderman to be a member of the commission to check on conditions in Italy (ca. July 1917); Alderman to the Reverend Edward M. Deems, concerning possibly establishing a School of Religion as a memorial to Dr. Charles F. Deems at the University of Virginia (November 18, 1916); A.G. Delmarsh; Democratic National Committee; Ethel (Roosevelt) Derby; Alderman letters of condolence to Ernest Dewey; John Dewey; William E. Dold; Edwin T. Douglass, concerning fishing (August 24, 1921); Alderman to Dr. Fred J. Douglas, thanking him for his services when he broke his arm on vacation (September 20, 1921); William F. Drewry; Sir John Kinninment Dunlop; Philip Francis DuPont; Pierre D. DuPont; Lafayette Browne Eaton urging Alderman to visit old Bethel Academy, which they attended 48 years ago (May 11, 28, 1924) and mentioning the death of Major MacIntyre's wife (June 18, 1925); William Holding Echols (1859-1934) writes two letters of encouragement to Alderman (March 17, 1907 and January 3, 1911); the Reverend Robert Emmet Elmore (1878-?) concerning whether Alderman supported prohibition in a recent speech (August 7, 1930); Alderman to Mrs. A.W. Erickson concerning his upcoming Wilson speech and the recent deaths of three faculty, one each week (December 5, 1924); Nancy [Erickson?]; Moses Ezekiel (1844-1917) asking Alderman's help in financial matters and describing his work on a Confederate Monument for Arlington, Virginia (April 26 and May 31, 1911); Alderman to J.L. Farmer; Judge Charles E. Fenner concerning the offer of the University of Virginia presidency to Alderman (June 23, 1904) and Alderman's request for the support of the Peabody Fund for the University of Virginia chair of education (January 21, 1905); Alderman to Junius P. Fishburn concerning his willingness to speak at Finals (May 5, 1927); Alderman carbon letters to Dr. Abraham Flexner, General Education Board, concerning funds for the equipment for the Medical School of the University of Virginia from the Board (January 10, 1923; January 18, 1924, June 14, 1924; April 6, 14, 1927); James Carrol Flippin concerning plans for the Department of Surgery and Gynecology (April 5, 1927); Professor Alcee Fortier (1856-1914) Alderman voices his concern over the controversy surrounding the education bond issue which appears to be in peril of not passing the Louisiana Legislature (October 26, 1904); Mrs. W.W. Fuller; and H.R. Fulton (Box-folder 2:19)
  - 1901 Correspondence: Charles William Dabney (1855-1945), President of the University of Tennessee and member of the Southern Education Board, Alderman writes to Dabney concerning how he thinks they should organize the work with regional directors, with himself dealing with Louisiana and the southwestern territory (September 30, October 2, 1901) (Box-folder 2:20)
  - 1886-1923 Correspondence: Frank B. Dancy (d. 1922), fellow classmate at the University of North Carolina, lifelong friend, and later fishing companion, these are chiefly personal letters, including: Alderman's description of the wedding arrangements for his marriage to Emma Graves (December 8, 1886 [sic?]); "List of Fumtimical Words" (1880's); his pleasure at Alderman's election as President of the University of North Carolina (August 11, 1896) and his regret at being unable to attend the inauguration (January 8, 1897); discusses preparations for Alderman's marriage to Bessie Green Hearn (November 5, 1903 and January 22, 1904); Alderman mentions the death of his niece, Alice Green Wilson, from cancer, and the retirement of Charles W. Dabney (June 22, 1921); Alderman's relief on winning the battle over the medical school and Dancy's description of his own battle with a tarpon fish (March 1, 4, 8, 1922); and the death of Frank Dancy in the summer of 1922, on the afternoon of July 1 st (October 6, 1922; March 9, 1923). The letters dated 1923 are between Alderman and Mrs. Dancy ("Bessie") (Box-folder 2:21)
  - 1913-1929 Correspondence: Josephus Daniels (1862-1948), writes concerning his appointment by Woodrow Wilson to be Secretary of the Navy [March 2, 1913?]; and a copy of Alderman's message of greeting to the Home-Coming Celebration in North Carolina that he is unable to attend personally (October 3, 1929), also see printed speech in speech series (Box-folder 2:22)
  - 1918-1919, n.d. Correspondence: Westmoreland Davis, appointing Alderman to represent Virginia at the Win the War for Permanent Peace Convention at Philadelphia (April 15, 1918) and as an Honorary Delegate to the Atlantic Congress for a League of Nations, letter and oversize certificate (January 22, 1919) (Box-folder 2:23)
  - 1901-1925 Correspondence: Charles William Eliot (1834-1926), draft of a letter of Alderman about the invitation to deliver the lectures at Cambridge under the Noble Foundation (September 9, 1902); urging Alderman to use the death of Archer Christian in a football game at Georgetown as an occasion to speak out against the inordinate risks of the game due to its current rules, with Alderman's reply (November 14 and 18, 1909); program honoring the 90 th birthday of Eliot (March 20, 1924); and his favorable response to Alderman's speech on Woodrow Wilson (January 9, 1925) (Box-folder 2:24)
  - 1920-1931 Correspondence: Alfred William Erickson (1876-1936), largely social letters about the exchange of book recommendations, book gifts and fishing, but also including Alderman's critique and defense of Woodrow Wilson (November 8, 1920); Alderman's criticism of the speech by Warren G. Harding (December 9, 1920); Erickson' agreement with the assessment of Wilson found in Lansing's book, which he has given to Alderman (March 25, 1921); mention of Alderman's "victory celebration" concerning the medical education fight in Virginia (March 3, 1922); invitation to the Megantic Fishing Preserve in Maine (May 26, 1922); mentions the death of Frank Dancy Saturday afternoon on [July 1, 1922?] (July 8, 1922); reference to the Teapot Dome scandal (February 9, 18, 1924); membership in the Megantic Fish and Game Corporation (March 10, 1924; May 21, 1924); and some difficulties in the life of a college president (June 17, 1925) (Box-folder 2:25)
  - 1908-1912, 1920-1931 Correspondence: Family, includes letters to and from his sisters, Alice West (d. 1915) and Ida Green (d. 1926); brother-in-law, Hector M. Green (1849-?); cousins Annie Saunders, Aline G. Saunders, Jennie Alderman McCall, Henrietta (Alderman) Murphy, Robert J. Murphy, Belle H. Hawley and Annie Royal Saunders; niece Mary Graves Rees; other relatives, L.R. Alderman, Hugh Wilson; topics include: Alderman genealogy (October 1, 1912; April 10, 1911); references to Woodrow Wilson or the Wilson Memorial speech by Alderman (October 1, 1912; December 6, 11, 18, 1924); divorce of Mary Graves Rees and request for character reference (January 10, 18, 1924); death of Alice Green Wilson (June 27, 1921); death of Frank Dancy (July 5, 1922); Billy Sunday lecture (April 13, 1923); Alderman's opinion about H.L. Mencken (February 4, 1925); the death of Hector Green while Alderman was away on his European trip (October 22, 1925); death of his sister, Ida Green, on April 9 th (April 19, 20, and May 17, 1925); death of Dr. George H. West (February 1, 1928); marriage of Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (October 15, 18, 1929); and boxing activities of Hugh Wilson (January 10, 1930) (Box-folder 3:1)
  - 1904-1932 Correspondence: John H. Finley, chiefly social letters of greeting or references to Alderman speeches but include a letter about the death of Warren G. Harding that occurred while Finely was traveling in Turkey (August 10, 1923) (Box-folder 3:2)
  - 1924, 1929 Correspondence: Thomas Staples Fuller, Alderman solicits funding to begin the Virginia Quarterly Review (July 17, 1924) (Box-folder 3:3)
  - 1908-1915 Correspondence: Williamson Whitehead Fuller (1858-1934), member of the Board of Trustees for the UVA Alumni Endowment Fund, writes winsome reports about his life on his farm, "Briarcliff Manor" New York, and encouraging letters during Alderman's illness while at Saranac and during the course of Alderman's career; other topics include details from Alderman about the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Endowment Fund (November 11, 1908); gift of the artist proof of the engraving of George Washington by W.E. Marshall (June 20, 1909); the gift of O.H. Payne to Alderman when he was sick at Saranac (December 11, 1912); mentions the sermon "Still Small Voice" and visit of Dr. [John Henry] Jowett to Briarcliff Church (May 19, 1913); the scandal concerning the offering of an appointment of Henry Means Pindell, of Peoria, Illinois, as ambassador to Russia (November 11, 1913); disappointment with Woodrow Wilson (June 26, 1914); John Blackwell Cobb (1857- ?) has agreed to give $50,000 towards a chemistry laboratory for the University (March 20, 26 and April 3, 1915) (Box-folder 3:4)
  - 1916-1922 Correspondence: Williamson Whitehead Fuller (1858-1934), inquires about Alderman's work with the Legislature for funding which is hampered by Virginia's new system of taxation (February 21, 23, 1916); the outbreak of war (April 6, 1917); marriage of Fuller's daughter (April 9, 1917); Alderman's desire for a botanical garden at the University (ca. April 1917); impact of the war upon the University's finances (April 17, 1917); death of [O.H. Payne] apparently imminent, Payne died on June 27 th (May 26, 1917); death of Dr. Lewis A. Stimson (September 20, 22, 1917); meeting with Gutzon Borglum to arrange work on a McConnell monument at the University and payment for the work (January 9, 11, 1918; April 7, July 7, 10, 17, 1919); Fuller's benefits to the University (March 24, 1919); the election of 1920 (November 8, 1920); Alderman broke his arm six weeks ago (August 26, 1926); and the portrait of Alderman (April 15, December 26, 1922) (Box-folder 3:5)
  - 1923-1930 Correspondence: Williamson Whitehead Fuller (1858-1934), mentions the death of [John Blackwell] Cobb (April 12, 23, 26, 1923); reactions to the speech of Homer Cummings (June 16, 19, 1923); predictions and analysis of the upcoming presidential race (July 21, 1923); unveiling of the Aycock Statue in Raleigh North Carolina (February 24, 1924); Cummings handling of the Harold Israel murder case (January 10, 12, 1925); anguish over Professor Lefevre and his drinking party (June 30, 1925); Fuller's speech concerning Malbourne A. Angier, mayor of Durham, North Carolina (1820-1900); stroke of servant Sarah Goins (October 28, 1926); the story of the will of James McAllister to appear in the Virginia Quarterly Review (October 30, 1926 through March 17, 1927); copy of Fuller's letter to Alfred E. Smith (April 22, 1927); the gift from the alumni to Alderman (June 29, 1929); and Robert B. Tunstall and the limitations on the use of the alumni fund, especially as concerns a pension fund for presidents (September 17, 18, 1929, and attached) (Box-folder 3:6)
  - 1900-1931 Correspondence: G, including: Charles B. Galloway; Alderman to F.T. Gates, General Education Board concerning the University of Virginia Medical School (March 24, 1925); Wendell P. Garrison, concerning Alderman's speech in New Orleans on December 29, 1903, and his viewpoint on racial integrity (March 7, 1904); George H. Denny, President of the University of Alabama, to the General Education Board, concerning the need for financial support to improve faculty salaries (March 18, 1920); Alderman to P.H. Gentry, [Albemarle County Supervisor?] expressing the need for a strong local public health department (March 12, 1924); Georgia, University of, offering Alderman the Chancellorship of the University of Georgia by telegram (June 12, 1925); R.W. Gilder concerning a list of prominent Southern men (March 31, 1901); Basil L. Gildersleeve, refers to his past association with the University and the medal presented to him during the Centennial (December 1, 1911 and June 17, 1921); D.G. Gilman, asking Alderman to succeed Dr. Curry on the Board of the Peabody Fund which he refuses (December 15, 31,1903); Arthur Glasgow; Ellen Anderson Gholson Glasgow tries to answer Alderman's question about her views on the contribution of the South to the character of the nation (February 5, 1903); Alderman to Harriet W. Glenn; Sydney Godfrey; Alexander Graham; Edward K. Graham; John Graham; John W. Graham: Charles Alfred Graves, UVA Law Department; Frances Griffith Graves sends a post card photograph of "Albenia" Lake George, New York (October 19, 1926); Fannie Graves; Julia C. Graves; Louis Graves; Ralph H. Graves; Dr. Cary T. Grayson, Guy M.Green; and Alderman to Samuel Abbott Green concerning the distribution of the Peabody Fund (March 16, 1905) (Box-folder 3:7)
  - 1906-1922 Correspondence: Frederick Taylor Gates (1853-1929), informs Alderman that John D. Rockefeller will contribute $100,000 toward the completion of the million dollar fund as a memorial to his friend, J.L.M. Curry by founding a school of education in his name (April 13, 1905); describes his objective with the University of Virginia and pleads with the General Education Board to contribute $50,000 to education in each of the eleven Southern states (January 22, 1909); Alderman's idea of the General Education Board helping the Southern universities develop an extension service to go out into the communities (October 14, 1911); urges the General Education Board to donate $100,000 toward the Centennial Fund (May 11, 17, 19, 20, 1921) and discusses Gates desire to retire from the Board (November 13, 1922) (Box-folder 3:8)
  - 1918-1931 Correspondence: Carter Glass, mutual notes of congratulations, especially concerning Alderman's speech on Wilson (1924) (Box-folder 3:9)
  - 1909-1930 Correspondence: Armistead Churchill Gordon (1855-1931), Rector of the University of Virginia, includes both social and University related letters, including: Alderman's report of the educational and financial operations of the University of Virginia for the past year (October 29, 1909); two incomplete letters from Gordon expressing concern over Alderman's health (ca. 1912-1913); Alderman's opinion on the medical college (January 27, 1914); and a full statement about his position on the co-ordinate women's college in Virginia (December 2,1915) (Box-folder 3:10)
  - 1897-1931 Correspondence: H, including Arthur Twining Hadley, President of Yale; Dr. Louis V. Hammam, Johns Hopkins Hospital; John F. Harmon; William Rainey Harper (1856-1906), President of the University of Chicago; Daisy Harriman, Woman's National Democratic Club, asking permission to use his Memorial Address on Woodrow Wilson in a book about democracy (August 30, 1930); Harris & Ewing Photographers of National Notables; Charles Custis Harrison (1844-1929), Provost of the University of Pennsylvania; Duncan B. Harrison concerning his national march hymnal, "Our Flag of Liberty" (February 7, 1931 and attached); Henry Sydnor Harrison; Alderman to Harris Hart, Superintendent of [Virginia] Public Instruction; Franklin A. Harwood concerning the death of his four year old son (November 20, 1927); Henry S. Haskell, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace sending a bronze medal, not present (March 6, 1925); Dr. Archibald Henderson; Alderman to David Hepburn concerning prohibition (May 28, 1924); John Grier Hibben (1861-1931); John D. Hilton; Alderman to Mrs. Hitchcock; Richmond Fearson Hobson (1870-1937); letter to W.T. Hodges from Alderman, furnishing information about housing needs for both female graduate students and male students (October 15, 1925); Dr. M.D. Hoge, Jr. congratulating Alderman on the honor bestowed upon him at Harvard (October 13, 1909); Peyton H. Hoge concerning the death of Alderman's sister, Ida Green (April 16, 1926); Winifred McCall Holhan; I.S. Hopkins, sharing his appreciation for the Library of Southern Literature (November 20, 1930); Edward Mandell House (1858-1938) memories of Walter Hines Page, Woodrow Wilson's plans for Alderman and the Wilson Administration (November 26, 1922); Herbert Sherman Houston (1865-1955), enclosing a copy of his tribute to Walter Hines Page (August 29, 1930); William D. Howells (1837-1919) (September 24, 1912), original transferred to the Vault-Autographs; Charles Evans Hughes (1862-1948), Secretary of State, concerning Alderman's comments about his retirement (January 23, 1925); Alderman to Robert M. Hughes; Thomas Lomax Hunter, Alderman comments favorably about his column in the Times Dispatch of January 14 (January 15, 1931); and Eppa Hunton, Jr.(1855-1932) (Box-folder 3:11)
  - 1922 April 13 Correspondence: Warren G. Harding (1865-1923), President of the United States, declines an invitation to come to the University of Virginia graduation and mentions Senator Oscar Wilder Underwood, original transferred to the Vault-Autographs (Box-folder 3:12)
  - 1909-1931 Correspondence: Mr. and Mrs. James W. Hearn, the father and mother-in-law of Edwin A. Alderman, chiefly family and social news (Box-folder 3:13)
  - 1926-1930 Correspondence: Herbert Hoover (1874-1964), President of the United States, concerning a request for Alderman to serve on a commission in Haiti and other requests for speeches both to Alderman and Hoover; originals transferred to the Vault-Autographs; also includes some copies of Alderman's letters from the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library (Box-folder 3:14)
  - 1903, 1917-1931 Correspondence: David Franklin Houston (1866-1940), Secretary of Agriculture and Secretary of the Treasury, answers Alderman's question about the contribution of the South to the nation (February 23, 1903); Alderman's concern over the world's situation, his opinion of Wilson, and his belief that war with Germany is virtually inevitable (March 22, 1917); Houston's impressions of Walter Hines Page (April 4, 1919); his response to the article about himself written by Alderman -see the article "One Man's Secret of Success" from The Independent in the article and speech series (December 24, 29, 1920); Houston's impression of Woodrow Wilson after the election (January 3, 1921); list of some of Woodrow Wilson's qualities and services for Alderman's memorial speech (April 22, December 13, 18, 1924); and the scandal of Sir Frederick Whyte who eloped with a Baroness he met in Shanghai while on duty in China for Great Britain in the summer of 1930 (February 9, 1931) (Box-folder 3:15)